<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="faces.messages">
	<title>Exception Handling</title>
  <para>
    Seam Faces makes use of Solder Exception Handling, coupled with JSF2 exception handlers to provide a robust and
    complete means of handling exceptions that occur in a JSF application. For more information about using Solder
    Exception Handling, please see <xref linkend="catch-introduction"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
    All exceptions that occur during the JSF life cycle should be caught by Seam Faces and passed along to Solder
    Exception Handling. There may be a few cases where this doesn't happen, fortunately, a Solder servlet filter
    acts as a catch all for exceptions and will pass along the uncaught exception.
  </para>
  <warning>
    <para>
      Something that must be considered when handling an exception within the JSF life cycle is the phase in which the 
      exception occurred. Most exceptions can be handled easily and a <literal>FacesMessage</literal> can be added and
      displayed to the user, or the user can be redirected to an error page. However, if the exception occurred in the
      <literal>RENDER_RESPONSE</literal> phase this is not the case. No redirection, or messages, or other output to 
      the response can be used if the request is in this part of the life cycle. Please inject the 
      <literal>FacesContext</literal> and determine the life cycle phase of the request before proceeding with exception 
      handling.
    </para>
  </warning>
  <section>
    <title>Qualifier</title>
    <para>
      All exceptions that are passed to Solder Exception Handling from within Seam Faces have the <literal>Faces</literal>
      qualifier added to them. This can aid in exception handling by limiting the exception handlers (based on qualifier)
      which are notified of the exception.
    </para>
</chapter>
