<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="components">
	<title>Seam Faces Components</title>
	<para>
		While Seam Faces does not provide layout components or other UI-design related features, it does provide
		functional components designed to make developing JSF applications easier, more functional, more
		scalable, and more practical.
	</para>

	<para>
		For layout and design components, take a look at <ulink
		url="http://jboss.org/richfaces">RichFaces</ulink>, a UI component library specifically tailored for
		easy, rich web-interfaces.
	</para>

	<section id="basicUsage">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			In order to use the Seam Faces components, you must first add the namespace to your view file, 
			just like the standard JSF component libraries.
		</para>
			
		<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
   xmlns:f="http://java.sun.com/jsf/core"
   xmlns:h="http://java.sun.com/jsf/html"
   xmlns:s="http://jboss.org/seam/faces"
   xmlns:ui="http://java.sun.com/jsf/facelets">
      
   <h1>Welcome to Seam Faces!</h1>
   <p>
      This view imports the Seam Faces component library.
      Read on to discover what components it provides.
	</p>
      
</html>]]></programlisting>
		<tip>
			<para>
				All Seam Faces components use the following namespace: 
				<literal>http://jboss.org/seam/faces</literal>
			</para>
		</tip>

	</section>

	<section id="validateForm">
		<title>&lt;s:validateForm&gt;</title>
		<para>
			On many occasions you might find yourself needing to compare the values of multiple input fields
			on a given page submit: confirming a password; re-enter password; address lookups; and so on. 
			
			Performing cross-field form validation is simple - just place the &lt;s:validateForm&gt; component
			in the form you wish to validate, then attach your custom Validator.
		</para>

		<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<h:form id="locationForm">
   <h:inputText id="city" value="#{bean.city}" />
   <h:inputText id="state" value="#{bean.state}" />
   <h:inputText id="zip" value="#{bean.zip}" />
   <h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit" action="#{bean.submitPost}" />
                  
   <s:validateForm validatorId="locationValidator" />
</h:form>]]></programlisting> 

		<para>
			The corresponding Validator for the example above would look something like this:
		</para>

		<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@FacesValidator("locationValidator")
public class LocationValidator implements Validator
{
   @Inject
   Directory directory;

   @Inject
   @InputField
   private Object city;

   @Inject
   @InputField
   private Object state;

   @Inject
   @InputField
   private ZipCode zip;

   @Override
   public void validate(final FacesContext context, final UIComponent comp, final Object values)
         throws ValidatorException
   {
      if(!directory.exists(city, state, zip))
      {
         throw new ValidatorException(
            new FacesMessage("Sorry, that location is not in our database. Please try again."));
      }
   }
}]]></programlisting>
		
		<tip>
			<para>
				You may inject the correct type directly.
				<programlisting><![CDATA[@Inject
@InputField
private ZipCode zip;]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</tip>
		
		<para>
			Notice that the IDs of the inputText components match the IDs of your Validator 
			@InputFields; each @Inject @InputField member will be injected with the value of the form input field
			who's ID matches the name of the variable.
		</para>

		<para>
			In other words - the name of the @InputField annotated member variable will automatically
			be matched to the ID of the input component, unless overridden by using a field
			ID alias (see below.) 
		</para>
			
		<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<h:form id="locationForm">
   <h:inputText id="cityId" value="#{bean.city}" />
   <h:inputText id="stateId" value="#{bean.state}" />
   <h:inputText id="zip" value="#{bean.zip}" />
   <h:commandButton id="submit" value="Submit" action="#{bean.submitPost}" />
                  
   <s:validateForm fields="city=cityId state=stateId" validatorId="locationValidator" />
</h:form>]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			Notice that "zip" will still be referenced normally; you need only
			specify aliases for fields that differ in name from the Validator @InputFields.
		</para>

		<tip>
			<para>
				<literal>Using @InputField("customID")</literal> with an ID override can also be used to specify a
				custom ID, instead of using the default: the name of the field. This gives you the ability to
				change the name of the private field, without worrying about changing the name of input fields in
				the View itself.
				<programlisting><![CDATA[@Inject
@InputField("state")
private String sectorTwo;]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</tip>

	</section>
	
	<section id="viewaction">
		<title>&lt;s:viewAction&gt;</title>

		<para>
			The view action component (<literal>UIViewAction</literal>) is an <literal>ActionSource2</literal>
			<literal>UIComponent</literal> that specifies an application-specific command (or action), using
			using an EL method expression, to be invoked during one of the JSF lifecycle phases proceeding Render
			Response (i.e., view rendering).
		</para>
		
		<para>
			View actions provide a lightweight front-controller for JSF, allowing the application to accommodate
			scenarios such as registration confirmation links, security and sanity checking a request (e.g.,
			ensuring the resource can be loaded). They also allow JSF to work alongside action-oriented
			frameworks, and existing applications that use them.
		</para>

		<section>
			<title>Motivation</title>

			<para>
				JSF employs an event-oriented architecture. Listeners are invoked in response to user-interface
				events, such as the user clicking on a button or changing the value of a form input. Unfortunately,
				the most important event on the web, a URL request (initiated by the user clicking on a link,
				entering a URL into the browser's location bar or selecting a bookmark), has long been overlooked in
				JSF. Historically, listeners have exclusively been activated on postback, which has led to the common
				complaint that in JSF, "everything is a POST."
			</para>

			<para>
				<emphasis>We want to change that perception.</emphasis>
			</para>

			<para>
				Processing a URL request event is commonly referred to as bookmarkable or GET support. Some GET
				support was added to JSF 2.0 with the introduction of view parameters and the pre-render view event.
				View parameters are used to bind query string parameters to model properties. The pre-render view
				event gives the developer a window to invoke a listener immediately prior to the view being rendered.
			</para>

			<para>
				<emphasis>That's a start.</emphasis>
			</para>

			<para>
				Seam brings the GET support full circle by introducing the view action component. A view action is
				the compliment of a <literal>UICommand</literal> for an initial (non-faces) request. Like its
				cohort, it gets executed by default during the Invoke Application phase (now used on both faces
				and non-faces requests). A view action can optionally be invoked on postback as well.
			</para>

			<para>
				View actions (<literal>UIViewAction</literal>) are closely tied to view parameters
				(<literal>UIViewParameter</literal>). Most of the time, the view parameter is used to populate the
				model with data that is consumed by the method being invoked by a <literal>UIViewAction</literal>
				component, much like form inputs populate the model with data to support the method being invoked
				by a <literal>UICommand</literal> component.
			</para>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Usage</title>

			<para>
				Let's consider a typical scenario in web applications. You want to display the contents of a blog
				entry that matches the identifier specified in the URL. We'll assume the URL is:
			</para>

			<programlisting>http://localhost:8080/blog/entry.jsf?id=10</programlisting>
			
			<para>
				We'll use a view parameter to capture the identifier of the entry from the query string and a view
				action to fetch the entry from the database.
			</para>

			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<f:metadata>
   <f:viewParam name="id" value="#{blogManager.entryId}"/>  
   <s:viewAction action="#{blogManager.loadEntry}"/>  
</f:metadata>]]></programlisting>

			<tip>
				<para>
					The view action component must be declared as a child of the view metadata facet (i.e.,
					<literal>&lt;f:metadata&gt;</literal>) so that it gets incorporated into the JSF lifecycle on both
					non-faces (initial) requests and faces (postback) requests. If you put it anywhere else in the
					page, the behavior is undefined.
				</para>
			</tip>

			<warning>
				<para>
					In JSF 2.0, there must be at least one view parameter for the view metadata facet to be processed.
					This requirement was introduced into the JSF specification accidentally, but it's not so
					unfortunate since view parameters are typically needed to capture input needed by the view action.
				</para>
			</warning>

			<para>
				What do we do if the entry can't be found? View actions support declarative navigation just like
				<literal>UICommand</literal> components. So you can write a navigation rule that will be consulted
				before the page is rendered. If the rule matches, navigation occurs just as though this were a
				postback.
			</para>

			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<navigation-rule>
      <from-view-id>/entry.xhtml</from-view-id>
      <navigation-case>
         <from-action>#{blogManager.loadEntry}</from-action>
         <if>#{empty entry}</if>
         <to-view-id>/home.xhtml</to-view-id>
         <redirect/>
      </navigation-case>
   </navigation-rule>]]></programlisting>

			<para>
				After each view action is invoked, the navigation handler looks for a navigation case that matches
				the action's EL method signature and outcome.  If a navigation case is matched, or the response is
				marked complete by the action, subsequent view actions are short-circuited. The lifecycle then
				advances appropriately.
			</para>

			<para>
				By default, a view action is not executed on postback, since the primary intention of a view
				action is to support a non-faces request. If your application (or use case) is decidedly stateless,
				you may need the view action to execute on any type of request. You can enable the view action
				on postback using the <literal>onPostback</literal> attribute:
			</para>
	
			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<s:viewAction action="#{blogManager.loadEntry}" onPostback="true"/>]]></programlisting>
	
			<para>
				You may only want the view action to be invoked under certain conditions. For instance, you may only
				need it to be invoked if the conversation is transient. For that, you can use the
				<literal>if</literal> attribute, which accepts an EL value expression:
			</para>
	
			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<s:viewAction action="#{blogEditor.loadEntry}" if="#{conversation.transient}"/>]]></programlisting>
	
			<para>
				There are two ways to control the phase in which the view action is invoked. You can set the
				<literal>immediate</literal> attribute to true, which moves the invocation to the Apply Request Values phase
				instead of the default, the Invoke Application phase.
			</para>
	
			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<s:viewAction action="#{sessionManager.validateSession}" immediate="true"/>]]></programlisting>
	
			<para>
				You can also just specify the phase directly, using the name of the phase constant in the
				<literal>PhaseId</literal> class (the case does not matter).
			</para>
	
			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<s:viewAction action="#{sessionManager.validateSession}" phase="APPLY_REQUEST_VALUES"/>]]></programlisting>
	
			<tip>
				<para>
					The valid phases for a view action are:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para><literal>APPLY_REQUEST_VALUES</literal> (default if <literal>immediate="true"</literal>)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><literal>UPDATE_MODEL_VALUES</literal></para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><literal>PROCESS_VALIDATIONS</literal></para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><literal>INVOKE_APPLICATION</literal> (default)</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</tip>

         <para>
            If the phase is set, it takes precedence over the immediate flag.
         </para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>View actions vs the PreRenderViewEvent</title>
			<para>
				The purpose of the view action is similar to use of the PreRenderViewEvent. In fact, the code to
				load a blog entry before the page is rendered could be written as:	
			</para>

			<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<f:metadata>
   <f:viewParam name="id" value="#{blogManager.entryId}"/>  
   <f:event type="preRenderView" listener="#{blogManager.loadEntry}"/>  
</f:metadata>]]></programlisting>

			<para>
				However, the view action has several important advantages:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>It's lightweight</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>It's timing can be controlled</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>It's contextual</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>It can trigger navigation</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				View actions are lightweight because they get processed on a non-faces (initial) request
				<emphasis>before</emphasis> the full component tree is built. When the view actions are invoked,
				the component tree only contains view metadata.
			</para>

			<para>
				As demonstrated above, you can specify a prerequisite condition for invoking the view action,
				control whether it's invoked on postback, specify the phase in which it's invoked and tie the
				invocation into the declarative navigation system. The PreRenderViewEvent is quite basic in
				comparison.
			</para>

		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
