<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="scopes">
	<title>Faces Scoping Support</title>
	<para>
		JSF 2.0 introduced the concept of the @ViewScope, and the @FlashScope; however, CDI does not support the non-standard
		ViewScope by default, and JSF 2.0 did not provide annotations for accessing the FlashScope. The Seam Faces module
		does both.
	</para>
	<section id="viewscoped">
		<title>@ViewScope</title>
		<para>
			To scope a bean to the View, use the <literal>@javax.faces.bean.ViewScoped</literal> annotation. This means that your bean will be stored in the 
			<literal>javax.faces.component.UIViewRoot</literal> object associated with the view in which it was accessed. Each JSF view (faces-page) will store
			its own instance of the bean, just like each HttpServletRequest has its own instance of a @RequestScoped bean.
			<programlisting>@ViewScoped
public class Bean {
	// ...
}</programlisting>
			<caution>
				<para>
					@ViewScoped beans are destroyed when the JSF UIViewRoot object is destroyed. This means that the
					life-span of @ViewScoped beans is dependent on the <literal>javax.faces.STATE_SAVING_METHOD</literal> employed by the application itself.
				</para>
			</caution>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="flashscoped">
		<title>@FlashScope</title>
		<para>
			To scope a bean to the Flash, use the <literal>@javax.faces.bean.FlashScoped</literal> annotation. This means that your bean will be stored in the 
			<literal>javax.faces.context.Flash</literal>; however, the Flash is independent of the JSF view, and independent of the Request object. Objects stored in the
			Flash will survive one page request, then be destroyed after processing of the next subsequent request. As such, the Flash scope
			can be thought of as a scope that spans two requests; objects are added to the Flash during the first request, then removed from
			the Flash and destroyed after the second request.
			<programlisting>@FlashScoped
public class Bean {
	// ...
}</programlisting>
			<caution>
				<para>
					@FlashScoped beans are destroyed when the Flash is cleared. This means that the
					life-span of @FlashScoped beans is limited to two HTTP requests.
				</para>
			</caution>
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>